皆さんを歓迎いたします
Warm greetings to one and all.
The final session of our “Powerful by Faith!”
「信仰によって強くなる」地区大会の
最後の部が始まります
Regional Convention is about to begin.
As you watch the music-video presentation,
次のミュージックビデオを見ながら
reflect on how strong faith
忠誠が試みられる時に
信仰がどう役立つか考えましょう
helps us triumph
when our integrity is tested.
Please enjoy the video.
ビデオをお楽しみください
We have now reached
the final portion of this convention.
今年の地区大会も
残りわずかとなりました
In this session,
この部では 聖書の預言が
どのように信仰を強めるかを考え
we’ll see how Bible prophecy
strengthens our faith
and we’ll take an exciting look ahead
at future events.
将来起こる素晴らしい事柄
について取り上げます
First, let’s sing a song that expresses
まず 信仰を持ち続けるという
決意を表す歌を歌いましょう
our determination to exercise faith.
The song is number 126, entitled
126番の歌で
題は「目を覚ましていて
しっかり立ち 強い人になる」です
“Stay Awake, Stand Firm, Grow Mighty.”
Again, that’s song number 126.
126番の歌を歌いましょう
Earlier, we saw how Daniel the prophet
ドラマの第1部で 若い時の
ダニエルの信仰を見ました
showed faith as a young man.
What further tests lie ahead,
その後どんなことがあり エホバは
どのようにダニエルを助けたでしょうか
and how did Jehovah strengthen him?
We now invite you
to watch Part II of the drama
「ダニエル 信仰を貫いた人」という
ドラマの第2部をご覧ください
Daniel: A Lifetime of Faith.
あったぞ！
Over here!
ネボ イシュタル マルドゥク！
Hail Nebo, Ishtar,
and Marduk—greatest god of all!
偉大な神々に乾杯！
乾杯！
Yah!
賢人たちを呼べ
Call the wise men.
賢人たちを呼ぶんだ！
Call the wise men!
何だこれは？
I don’t know what that is.
お告げでもなさそうだ・・・
It doesn’t appear to be an omen.
こんなものは見たことがない
There’s nothing in the books, is there?
ほかに賢人はいないのか！
Are these all the wise men?
これで全員です
The best in the kingdom.
王に会わせてください
Please, I need to speak to the king!
The queen mother, my lord.
母上さまがいらっしゃいました
O king, may you live on forever.
王がいつまでも生き続けますように
There’s a man in your kingdom
この王国には 聖なる神々の
力を持つ人がいます
who has the spirit of the holy gods.
He will tell you the interpretation.
彼なら解き明かせるでしょう
Who is this man?
誰ですか
Daniel.
ダニエルです
Daniel?
ダニエル？知らない
Who’s Daniel?
Are you Daniel?
ダニエルか？
I am, my lord.
そうです
聞くところによると
I’ve heard concerning you
あなたは解き明かしができるそうだな
that you’re able to provide interpretations.
Now, if you are able to read the writing
もし この文字を読んで
意味を解き明かせるなら
and make its interpretation known to me,
あなたに紫の衣を着せ
you will be clothed with purple,
a gold necklace will be placed around your neck,
金の首飾りを掛け
この王国の第3の地位を与えよう
and you will rule as the third one in the kingdom.
You may keep your gifts.
贈り物は必要ありません
褒美はほかの人にお与えください
Give your presents to others.
ですが 私はこの文字を
王にお読みします
However, I will read the writing to the king.
The Most High God granted to Nebuchadnezzar
至高の神はネブカドネザルに
the kingdom and greatness
王国と偉大な力と
栄誉と威光を与えました
and honor and majesty.
しかし 心が傲慢になった時
But when his heart became haughty,
he was brought down from the throne of his kingdom
王座から降ろされ
尊厳を奪われました
and his dignity was taken away.
But you, Belshazzar—
ところが あなたベルシャザルは
You have not humbled your heart,
この全てを知りながら
謙遜になっていません
although you knew all of this.
Instead,
かえって 天の主に対して高ぶり
you exalted yourself against the Lord of the heavens.
その神の家の器を持ってこさせました
You had them bring you the vessels of His house.
And then you and your nobles,
そして あなたと貴族たち
your concubines and secondary wives
また側室やそばめたちは
それを使ってぶどう酒を飲み
drank wine from them
and praised the gods of silver and gold
銀や金でできた神々を賛美しました
その神々は見ることも
聞くこともできません
—gods who see nothing
and hear nothing
もちろん何も知りません
and know nothing.
But you’ve not glorified the God
それなのにあなたは
あなたの命を支えている
神をたたえてはいません
in whose hand is your breath
and all your ways.
そのため 手が
So the hand was sent from Him.
神から送られたのです
This is the interpretation of the words:
意味を解き明かしましょう
MENE:
メネ
God has numbered the days of your kingdom
神はあなたの王国の
日数を数えて終わらせた
and brought it to an end.
テケル
TEKEL:
You have been weighed in the balances
あなたはてんびんで量られて
and found lacking.
不足があった
PERES:
ペレス
Your kingdom has been divided
王国は分けられて
and given to the Medes
メディア人と
ペルシャ人に与えられた
and the Persians.
ダリウス王 ダニエルです
King Darius, this is Daniel
バビロンに連れてこられたユダヤ人です
—a Jew taken captive by the Babylonians.
Did you interpret the handwriting from the gods?
あなたが文字を あの文字を
解き明かしたのか？
No.
いいえ
私ではありません
Not me, O king
—my God—
私の神 イスラエルの神です
the God of Israel.
We could use a satrap
別の民族のことが分かっている
知事がいると助かる
who understands the captives.
I confess, a satrap
いや待てよ 知事だとベルシャザルの
申し出た立場よりも格が低い
is not as prominent a position
as Belshazzar granted you.
My lord, Daniel refused
ダニエルはベルシャザルが
申し出た褒美を断っています
every gift and honor Belshazzar offered him.
こんな人物がいたのか
A man without a price.
We don’t need you as a satrap
知事ではもったいない
—we need you over them.
あなたには知事たちを監督してもらおう
Tura,
トゥラ このことを帝国中に
知らせなさい
pronounce Daniel’s appointment
throughout the kingdom.
I want those stealing from the treasury to know
公費を横領している者たちを
取り締まってもらおう
that they will now be held accountable.
Daniel,
ダニエル あなたが高官だと安心です
you’ll make a fine high official.
エホバに頼るしかありません
Only with Jehovah’s help.
この土地の税金は高過ぎる
Why is the land tax so high?
また払わないやつがいるのか？
Another revolt?
面倒なことになってます
This is far more troubling.
役人が集めた土地の税金なんですけど
I just collected the land tax from an administrator.
ちゃんと持ってきたのか？
Did he pay?
はい
Yes, but he refuses to give us “our fees.”
でも“手数料”は入ってませんでした
うちもそうだ
I’ve had the same problem.
They’re calling anything more than the tax extortion.
決められた額以上は
収めないと言うんです
どうしてだ？
What’s changed?
ダニエルのせいだな！
Daniel.
Have you offered him anything
ダニエルには たんまり
持たせてるんだろう？
to make him more reasonable?
何も受け取ろうとしません
He won’t take a shekel of silver.
全く欲がないみたいです
Daniel claims that what he receives
is more than enough.
そんな訳ないだろう！
Don’t be so naive!
He’s putting on a show of integrity for the king.
今は王の前で格好付けてるだけだ
It won’t last.
気にするな
Darius will tire of him soon enough.
そのうちぼろが出る
There seems to be a discrepancy in the taxes
国の税の扱いに不備があるようです
due the treasury, my lord.
そうか よく言ってくれた
You’re brave to say that here.
残念な話ですが
I know it’s hard to hear.
この件は調査させよう
We will review the evidence.
ダニエル あなたはかなり
経験を積んでいるようだが
Daniel, your time here has given you much wisdom.
ここに来て長いのか？
How long have you been here?
Over 70 years.
かれこれ70年です
教えてくれないか
Share more with me.
Tell me about the dreams
あなたがネブカドネザルに
解き明かした夢のことを
you interpreted for Nebuchadnezzar.
Interpretations belong to my God,
解き明かすのは私の神エホバです
Jehovah.
エホバが明らかにしてくださったのです
He revealed the dreams to me.
Have I really been in Babylon over 70 years?
バビロンに来て70年か
そうだ エレミヤの預言だ
Jeremiah’s prophecy!
「70年が満了した時
“When 70 years have been fulfilled,
私は 過ちを犯したバビロンの
王と国民に責任を問う」
“I will call to account the king of Babylon
and that nation for their error.”
Belshazzar’s death
ベルシャザルが殺されたことだ
—it’s been fulfilled!
預言通りだ！
What does this mean for God’s people?
神の民はどうなるんだろう？
「バビロンで70年が満了したら
“When 70 years at Babylon are fulfilled,
私はあなたたちに注意を向ける
“I will turn my attention to you,
“and I will make good my promise
私の約束を果たし
あなたたちをこの場所に連れ戻す」
by bringing you back to this place.”
Judah!
ユダの地だ！
I must approach Jehovah
エホバに祈り
イスラエルの罪を告白しなくては
to confess the sin of my people.
O Jehovah,
エホバ
聞いてください
do hear,
お許しください
do forgive.
私たちに注意を向けて
O Jehovah, do pay attention and act.
救ってください！
Do not delay, for your own sake,
あなたご自身のために
行動を遅らせないでください
O my God.
O Daniel,
ダニエル
私はあなたに洞察と理解を
与えるために来ました
now I have come to give you insight
and understanding.
When you began your entreaty,
あなたが懇願し始めた時に
the word went out,
神が述べられた言葉を伝えに来ました
and I have come to report it to you.
あなたの民と聖なる都市のために
70週が定められました
There are 70 weeks that have been determined
for your people and your holy city
これは 違反を終わらせ
罪をなくし⋯⋯
in order to terminate the transgression,
to finish off sin.
ダニエル アザルエルと
ハンナが来ましたよ
Daniel, Azarel and Hannah are here.
Hello, Daniel.
こんにちは
It’s so good to see you!
よく来たね！
エフェル こっちへおいで
Epher, come sit with me.
いいことがあったんだ
I have good news!
何があったんですか？
What’s the good news?
エホバは昔 私たちがユダに
戻れるとおっしゃった
Jehovah has long told us
that we will return to Judah.
エレミヤの預言をもう一度確かめたんだ
I looked again at Jeremiah’s prophecy:
“This is what Jehovah says,
「エホバはこう言う
“‘When 70 years at Babylon are fulfilled, . . .
『バビロンで70年が満了したら
“‘I will make good my promise
私は⋯⋯約束を果たし
あなたたちをこの場所に連れ戻す』」
by bringing you back to this place.’”
「70年」とあるから
“Seventy years.”
もうすぐ帰れるということだ
That means God’s people will return soon.
どうして分かったんですか？
How can you be sure?
天使が来て教えてくれたんだ
Jehovah sent an angel to tell me.
天使が来たの？
An angel?
こう言ったんだ
He said that the city
「都市と神殿は建て直される
and its temple will be rebuilt,
そしてメシアが現れる」と
and the Messiah will finally come!
エフェル 新しい神殿を
見ることができるよ
You will get to see the temple rebuilt.
But won’t it be dangerous?
旅は危険じゃないですか？
Jehovah is eager
エホバはご自分の民を
助けたいと思っている
to fulfill the needs of his people.
イザヤにこう告げた
He told Isaiah
「生まれる子たちが苦しむことはない
that we ‘won’t bear children for distress,
‘for they’re the offspring
彼らとその子孫は エホバに
祝福された民だからである」
made up of those blessed by Jehovah.’
エホバが言ったことは・・・
And if Jehovah says it,
必ず起きる！
it’s as good as done!
でも土地は荒れています
But isn’t the land desolate?
だから腕のいい職人さんが
大勢必要なんだよ
That’s why we’ll need skilled builders
for the restoration work.
ダニエルもユダに一緒に行くの？
Does this mean you’ll return to Judah?
いやあ 行きたいなあ
I sure hope so.
まず道路の整備をお願いします
Have a team of workers maintain the roads.
Otherwise, conditions will only worsen
雨期になったら工事は難しいですから
during the rainy season.
トゥラ 手配しなさい
Tura, see that it’s done.
それにしても
いろんなことを知ってますね
How is it that you know so much?
I can’t take credit, my lord.
とんでもありません 私はただ・・・
I just . . .
この国には 王のお役に立つ
専門家が大勢いますから
We have many great men
who provide the information we need, O king.
ダニエル
Daniel,
about that satrap in Susa.
スサの知事についてだが
更迭した方がよいか？
Should he be replaced?
調べてもらいましたが
My men have thoroughly investigated,
その知事は国のお金を着服していました
間違いありません
and the satrap has been diverting palace money
to his own pocket.
That’s—that’s impossible!
そんなはずはない！
Isn’t he your nephew, Otanes?
あなたの親族だったな オタネス
Indeed, and I can vouch for his integrity!
はい そうです そんなことをする
人間ではありません
何かの間違いでしょう
There must be some mistake.
彼のことはダニエルよりも
私の方がよく知っています
How can Daniel know his character as I do?
私がきちんと話をつけておきましょう
I will speak with him and resolve the matter.
We Medes and Persians
メディア人とペルシャ人は寛容です
are not as intolerant as these Jews.
ユダヤ人たちよりも
こちらで何とかします
I’m sure we can fix this.
Very well. Settle it quickly.
いいだろう 迅速にな 頼んだぞ
That will be all.
お断りしたんですが 勝手に・・・
My lord, I’m so sorry.
You have guests.
よくもまあこんなに祈れるもんですね
All you Jews do is pray.
王にお仕えするには神の助けが必要です
I could not serve the king
the way I do without God’s help.
王に仕える？
Serve the king
知事を首にしてですか？
by intimidating satraps?
当然のことをしたまでです
I’ve only done what I should.
よそ者にあれこれ指図されると
迷惑なんですよね
An outsider has no place telling us
how to conduct business.
王のためです
I act in the king’s interests.
ネブカドネザル王にしたことも
聞きましたよ
We’ve heard how you acted
in Nebuchadnezzar’s interests.
あなたのせいで気が狂った
You made him go insane.
あれはエホバが語ったことです
That was a message from Jehovah.
知りませんよ
Call it what you will,
ただ 私たちの邪魔はしないでください
but do not interfere with us.
知事1人首にするのと
If it seemed easy
ユダヤ人の年寄り1人片付けるのと
to remove a satrap,
think of how much easier it will be
どっちが簡単かよく考えてください
to get rid of an old Jew.
お呼びでしょうか
It’s an honor to be with you.
なぜ呼ばれたか分かっているだろうな？
Do you know why I summoned you?
いいえ
No, my lord.
ダニエルが問題にした知事だが
That satrap whose dismissal Daniel recommended
その後どうなったんだ？
—what’s become of him?
われわれもその件を
しっかり調査しました
Yes, we thoroughly investigated the matter.
問題はなかったのか？
Was there negligence?
None.
ありません
Any omission of duty?
一つもか？
Not at all.
はい
税は全て国に納められていたのか？
All taxes due the treasury have come to the treasury?
金もビールも全てきちんと
納められていました
Every shekel of gold and quart (1.08 L) of beer
are accounted for.
ダニエルの話とは随分違うな
Daniel reached a different conclusion.
ダニエルですか
Ah, Daniel—
バビロンの時代には
活躍していましたね・・・
He served the Babylonian kings well, but . . .
he’s so old!
あの年では・・・
What Otanes means is,
つまり あの年できちんと
仕事ができるのでしょうか
at Daniel’s age, how reliable is his judgment?
His ideas are outdated.
考えが古いんです
しかもユダヤ人ですよ
Besides, he is a Jew.
われわれは民族で差別はしない
Katu, we are tolerant of all peoples.
ええ 私も差別には反対です
Yes, of course. That’s my point.
Daniel, we were just talking about you.
ダニエル いいところに来た
ダニエルは正しかった
You were right.
スサの住民が暴動を起こした
There’s been a revolt in Susa.
They demand a new satrap
ピンはねをする
あの知事を替えてくれと
—one who doesn’t steal from them.
いや そんなはずは・・・
But my lord, surely . . .
いいかげんにしろ！
Enough!
I sent my own inspectors—men I trust!
私が自分で調べたんだ
Daniel, you’ve distinguished yourself over these men.
ダニエル あなたに並ぶ者は誰もいない
総理大臣になってくれたら
とても心強いのだが・・・
Imagine what I could do if you were my prime minister.
王に直訴しますか
Perhaps we could approach the king.
無駄だ 王はダニエルの言いなりだ
That’s no use.
Daniel’s manipulating him.
ダニエルを訴えるしかない
王が見過ごせない罪状で
We need an accusation against Daniel
—something that Darius can’t ignore.
彼は清廉潔白です
But no one has accused him of anything.
探せばある
Not yet.
Assemble a team to comb through our laws.
人を集めて書類を調べさせろ
何か出てくるはずだ
Surely he’s violated something.
You!
そっちは 商人や役人を調べ上げろ
Interview merchants, inspectors, officials
誰でもいい 協力者を探すんだ
—whoever will make an accusation against him.
Assure the accuser
協力者には しっかり渡してやれ
he will be generously rewarded.
We have the Babylonian records.
バビロニア時代の記録もある
なんでもいい
Search for any scandal that might implicate him.
使えるねたを探し出せ
何も出てきませんでした
There is nothing in the records.
Anything?
どうだ？
Not a shekel of silver is missing.
どれも金額はぴったりです
In fact, when Daniel gets involved,
ダニエルが扱うようになってから
corruption and loss go down.
腐敗も無駄もなくなりました
何か見つけてくれ
Keep searching.
No one will speak against him.
誰も悪口を言わない
They all love him,
みんなに慕われている
王の信頼もあつい
and he has the king’s trust.
Usually, the foreign merchants are ignored
普通 外国人の商人は
when they experience theft.
だまされても泣き寝入り
するしかないのに
However, Daniel stands up for them
ダニエルは外国人のために調査までする
and investigates.
そして きちんと弁償させる
He has thieves return whatever was stolen.
いつも一緒にいた3人の評判もいい
Even his friends are spotless.
Nebuchadnezzar once forbade anyone
その3人はバビロンの神を崇拝せず
to speak against their God.
Supposedly,
火の中に放り込まれた
this “Jehovah” saved them from the furnace
でも 彼らの神エホバとやらに
守られ 無傷だった
when they refused to worship a Babylonian god.
ほかの神々を崇拝しないのか？
Jews won’t worship other gods?
そのようです
So it would seem.
I think you’ve solved our problem.
これは使えるな
カトゥ オタネス 今度は何の用だ？
Katu, Otanes, what favor do you seek?
ダリウス王がいつまでも
生き続けますように
O King Darius, may you live on forever.
This Babylon of which you are king
バビロンは強固な都市ですが
人種のるつぼです
is mighty but diverse.
バビロニア人 エジプト人 ギリシャ人
その他もろもろです
There are Babylonians, Egyptians, Greeks, and others.
そんなことは知っている
Yes, Otanes, I know these things.
あなたは王ですが 外国人であり
征服したばかりです
You are the rightful king
but also a foreigner and a newcomer.
The people must adapt,
あなたの権威を示さないと
or the kingdom could become unstable.
国は不安定になってしまいます
What do you suggest?
何が言いたいんだ？
All royal officials,
あなたに仕える役人や長官
prefects, satraps,
知事や高官 総督が皆で協議した結果
high royal officers, and governors
have consulted together to establish a royal decree
次のような法令を制定していただくのが
よいということになりました
and to enforce a ban
30日の間 王以外の人や神に
請願をしてはならず
that for 30 days, whoever makes a petition
to any god or man
except to you, O king,
背いた者はライオンの穴に
投げ込まれる という禁令です
should be thrown into the lions’ pit.
The people are not above rebellion.
スサで起きたような暴動を
起こさせないためにも・・・
Look what happened in Susa.
Now, O king,
王よ この法令を制定し
may you establish the decree and sign it
ご署名くださいますように
so that it cannot be changed,
そうすれば変更できなくなります
according to the law of the Medes and the Persians,
メディアとペルシャの法律は
取り消すことができないからです
which cannot be annulled.
At this time,
この帝国は
our empire experiences peace and prosperity
いまだかつてないほどの
平和と繁栄に浴している
unlike ever seen before.
The recent acts of defiance in Susa,
最近スサで起きた暴動をはじめ
along with similar acts by small groups of radicals,
少数の過激派による同様の行為は
seek to undermine
our way of life
平和を脅かすものである
—a way of life we will sacrifice for nothing.
その平和は 何にも代え難い
In honor of the glorious freedom
この帝国によって与えられている
今の自由を守り
so kindly granted by the empire
またこの国の主権を守るため
and as a reminder of its sovereignty,
私メディア人ダリウスは
次の法令を定める
I, Darius the Mede,
make this decree:
For 30 days, anyone
30日の間
who makes a petition to any god or man,
王以外の人や神に請願をしてはならず
except to the king,
背いた者はライオンの穴に投げ込まれる
should be thrown into the lions’ pit.
まさか祈らないですよね？
You’re not going home to pray, are you?
アザルエル
Azarel,
you know me,
君たちも知っている
敵も知っている
and so do my enemies.
私は窓辺で祈っている
I pray at my window three times a day,
1日3回 毎日だ
every day.
If I even appear to compromise,
もし 窓辺で祈るのをやめたら
みんなはどう思うだろう？
what would they think?
That you stopped praying altogether.
祈るのをやめたと
それだけじゃない
Or even worse,
エホバを捨てたと思われる
that I’d trade my worship for my life.
命と引き換えに
エホバは私の友だ
I know Jehovah.
And if I trust him,
エホバを信頼すれば
報いてくださる
he’ll reward me.
I don’t know how,
どのようにかは分からない
でも必ず
but he will.
祈ってほしい
私が信仰を貫けるように
Pray that I keep my faith
みんなが信仰を貫けるように
—that we all keep our faith—
no matter how this ends.
どんなことがあっても
これをおまえにあげよう
I have something for you.
Dinner’s ready.
ご飯できたわよ
「エホバ救う・・・
“Jehovah is my light
強い手で 恐れない」
“and my salvation.
Whom should I fear?”
「エホバ
“Hear me, O Jehovah,
聞いてください
“when I cry out.
私が声を上げて呼ぶ時
“Show me favor
親切を示し
答えてください
“and answer me.
エホバ
“Your face, O Jehovah, I will seek to find.
私はあなたの好意を得ようと努めます
あなたは私を助ける方
“[For] you are my helper;
“do not forsake me
見捨てないでください
“or leave me,
放っておかないでください
私の救いの神」
my God of salvation.”
王がいつまでも生き続けますように
O king, may you live on forever.
Did you not sign a ban
ご署名になった禁令によれば
stating that for 30 days any man
30日の間 人や神に
請願をする者がいれば・・・
who makes a petition to any god or man
もちろん あなた以外にです・・・
—except to you, O king—
ライオンの穴に入れられますね？
should be thrown into the lions’ pit?
その通りだ メディアとペルシャの
法律は取り消すことができない
Yes, the matter is well-established
according to the law of the Medes and the Persians.
What’s your business?
何が言いたい？
ダニエルなんですが・・・
ユダから連れてこられた・・・
Daniel, who is of the exiles of Judah,
王に敬意を払わず
has paid no regard to you, O king,
あなたの禁令を無視しています
nor to the ban that you signed.
日に3度 神に祈っています
But three times a day,
he is praying.
Daniel?
ダニエルが？
It can’t be true.
そんなはずはない
Are you sure?
本当か？
あれは確信犯です
He doesn’t even try to deny it.
Were there witnesses?
目撃者はいたのか？
All five of us, my lord.
私たち5人全員です
We can attest to it.
彼は老人だ
But he is old.
Does he know what he’s doing?
判断が鈍ったのでは？
As a high official,
政府高官なので 立場は
わきまえているはずです
surely he understands what it means
to obey the king.
少し考える
Let me be.
逮捕しましょうか？
Should we arrest Daniel?
考えると言っているだろう！
Leave the matter to me!
Daniel should indeed be made an example of.
ダニエルは見せしめにする
高官の立場を解き
I’ll remove him from his post
明日の朝バビロンから追放する
and expel him from the city tomorrow morning.
お言葉ですが・・・
My lord . . .
民は 従わないなら
どうなるか分かるだろう
All will learn that our laws must be obeyed.
ですが法律では
But the law actually states that the accused
「ライオンの穴に投げ込む」
となっていますが
would be “thrown into the lions’ pit,” my lord.
I see what you’re doing!
そういうことか！恥ずかしくないのか
Have you no shame?
メディアとペルシャの法律によれば
The law of the Medes and the Persians
王が制定した禁令や法令は
一切変更できません
is that any ban or decree that the king establishes
cannot be changed.
We only wish the king to receive the honor
王の栄誉と安泰を願ったまでです
he deserves.
Take him to the pit.
では そのようにしろ
あなたが常に仕えている神が
Your God, whom you are continually serving,
あなたを救ってくださると
よいのだが・・・
will rescue you.
Remove the stone!
石をどけろ！
Daniel,
ダニエル
Daniel.
O king, may you live on forever.
王がいつまでも生き続けますように
生きてたぞ！引き上げろ！
He lives!
Bring him up!
天使が助けてくれました
My God sent his angel
and shut the mouths of the lions,
私の神が遣わして
ライオンの口をふさいでくれたので
and they have not harmed me,
無事です
for I was found innocent before him;
私は神の前で潔白です
nor have I done any wrong to you, O king.
王に対しても何も悪いことは
しておりません
アルメニアは私が頂こう
Armenia is mine.
Daniel let them off too easily.
ダニエルもあっけなかったな
We need their exceptional horses for our cavalry
アルメニアの馬は騎兵隊で使える
and a few for myself.
自分でも乗りたいし
いいだろう
アルメニアはやるよ
Fine, you take Armenia.
私はバクトリア地方がいい
宝石がある
I have my eye on Bactria and its precious stones.
早くもダニエルの領土の山分けですか？
Must you divide up Daniel’s kingdom now?
Check the back room!
ここにいたぞ！
What is the meaning of this?
何事だ？
You are being arrested
ダリウス王への反逆の罪で逮捕する！
for crimes against Darius the king!
The king ordered Daniel’s arrest, not ours.
それはダニエルの話だろ！
ダニエルは逮捕された
Daniel was arrested
今朝 無傷で穴から引き上げられた
and lifted from the pit this morning
—unharmed.
あり得ない
It can’t be!
The lions must have already been fed.
ライオンは満腹だったのか？
病気だったんですか？
Perhaps they were ill.
ライオンが病気？
The lions were ill?
満腹だった？
Not hungry?
家族もろとも穴に放り込め
Throw them and their families into the pit,
満腹かどうか分かるだろう
where they can test their theories.
王よ どうかご勘弁を！
No! Darius!
Don’t do this! I served you!
やめてください！
おやめください！
No! Don’t do this!
やめろ！
I served you!
は 放せ！
お許しください！
放せ！
No! Please!
お願いします！
王よ！
No!
私の王国の領土全域において
I am issuing an order
that in every domain of my kingdom,
民はダニエルの神の前で
畏れかしこまるように
people are to tremble in fear
この方こそ生きている神であり
before the God of Daniel.
永遠に存在されるからである
この方の王国は決して滅ぼされない
For he is the living God, and he endures forever.
His kingdom will never be destroyed.
この方は人を助け 救い
“He rescues,
“saves, and performs signs and wonders
天においても地においても奇跡や
不思議なことを行われる
“in the heavens and on the earth,
ダニエルをライオンの
爪から救ったのである
for he rescued Daniel from the paw of the lions.”
ダリウスが書かせたんですか？
Darius wrote that?
国中に書き送ったんだ
He’s sending it to all of his subjects.
心配したんですよ
We were so worried.
怖かった？
Were you scared?
怖かったよ でもそういうときに
エホバは助けてくれる
I was very scared,
but Jehovah helps us when we’re scared.
パパとママ エルサレムに
行くのが怖いんだって
They’re scared of going to Jerusalem.
Epher!
エフェルったら！
We’re still thinking about it.
まだ悩んでます
ダニエルは？帰るよね？
How about you? Are you going back?
王様 みんな帰っていいって言ってるよ
The king says we’re all allowed to go.
I’d love to go home,
帰りたいよ
but
でも
ちょっと遅過ぎたかな
I think it’s too late for me.
Then I don’t want to go either.
僕も行きたくない
Oh no, no, no, no.
そんなこと言わないで
Don’t cry.
エルサレムは 私がいた時よりも
素晴らしい町になる
If you go,
you’ll see a better city than the one I left.
You’ll see prophecies fulfilled,
預言がその通りになる
町はエホバを崇拝する人で
いっぱいになる
a city full of people worshipping Jehovah,
and a new temple
新しい神殿は
—the most beautiful building on earth.
世界で一番美しい建物になる
お隣のおじいちゃんに会った？
Did you see our old neighbor at all?
今日は会ってないわ
No, I didn’t him at all today.
おかしいのよエリったら
この間もね・・・
I saw our neighbor Eli the other day.
エホバから離れてはいけないよ
Stay close to Jehovah.
エホバは共にいてくださる
You will be blessed.
「私は1つのことをエホバに願い求めた
“One thing
“I have asked from Jehovah . . .
今も強く願っている
“that I might dwell
“in the house of Jehovah all the days of my life,
一生涯エホバの家に住むことを
“to gaze
エホバの
“upon the pleasantness of Jehovah
麗しさを見つめ
神の神殿を
“and to look
“with appreciation
感嘆して
眺めることを」
on his temple.”
ダニエル 少し休みましょう
Daniel, you need to rest.
O Daniel, you very precious man.
大切な人ダニエル
私は遣わされてきました
I have been sent to you.
Do not be afraid, Daniel.
恐れることはありません
あなたが謙遜になろうと
心に決めた最初の日から
Your words have been heard from the first day
you gave your heart to understanding
祈りは聞かれています
and humbling yourself before your God.
私が来たのは 最後の日々に
I have come to make you understand
あなたの民に起きる事柄を
理解させるためです
what will befall your people
in the final part of the days.
I have no strength.
もう力が出ません
息をするのも大変です
There’s no breath left in me.
大切な人ダニエル
恐れることはありません
Do not be afraid, O very precious man.
May you have peace.
大丈夫です
Be strong.
勇気を出してください
Be strong!
お話しください
Let my lord speak,
力が湧いてきました
for you have strengthened me.
I will tell you the things recorded
真実の書に記されている事柄を伝えます
in the writings of truth:
「さらに3人の王がペルシャの
ために立ち上がります
“Look!
“Three more kings will stand up for Persia,
4人目の王は他の王たちよりも
多くの富を築きます」
“and the fourth one will amass greater riches
than all others.”
これらの事柄はどんな結末を
迎えるのでしょうか
O my lord,
what will be the outcome of these things?
待ち続ける人は幸せです！
Happy is the one who keeps in expectation.
Go on to the end.
最後まで進んでいきなさい
You will rest,
あなたは休みますが 日々の終わりに
but you will stand up for your lot
報いを受けるために立ち上がります
at the end of the days.
If we eat those foods, we’ll disobey our God.
でも 食べると神に背くことになります
神を畏れているのか？
You fear your God?
I do.
そうです
私の神エホバなら解き明かせます
Interpretations belong to my God, Jehovah.
I know that he will reveal it to me.
必ず夢を解き明かしてくださいます
Jehovah
エホバは
is eager to fulfill the needs of his people.
ご自分の民を助けたいと思っている
I know Jehovah.
エホバは私の友だ
エホバを信頼すれば
And if I trust him,
報いてくださる
he’ll reward me.
I don’t know how,
どのようにかは分からない
でも必ず
but he will.
What an inspiring account!
本当に励まされました
Like Daniel,
ダニエルのように 私たちも
エホバから力と保護を得られます
we look to Jehovah
for strength and protection.
Our next song expresses
our confidence in him.
次の歌でエホバへの信頼を表せます
The song is entitled
“Seek God for Your Deliverance.”
歌の題は 「救いのために
神に頼る」です
Let’s sing together song number 150.
この150番の歌を歌いましょう
Again, that’s song number 150.
もう一度言います 150番の歌です